Fanny Ward Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
Fanny Ward Papers
1878 - 1895
The Fanny Ward Papers date from 1878 to 1895, with the bulk of the letters dating from 1879 to 1893. The collection consists of well over 100 letters discussing the mental illness of this young woman and showing the development and range of her illness over a period of fourteen years. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
.84 linear feet (2 boxes)
Ward, Frances Margaret
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1967.0001
The Fanny Ward Papers were purchased from the Old Hickory Bookshop in Brinklow, Maryland in 1967 with funds donated by Mr. and Mrs. Charles Blatt.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Frances Margaret Ward, known to her family, doctors and attendants as Fanny Ward, was dismissed from a girl’s school in England in the 19th century at age 15 due to mental illness. She blamed this situation on the death of her father, which had left her an orphan. The letters in this collection take Fanny up to age 29, at which time it appears that there was a slight possibility that she would be paroled if her exemplary behavior continued.
Chennai (India); England; hysteria; Ward, Frances Margaret
The Fanny Ward Papers date from 1878 to 1895, with the bulk of the letters dating from 1879 to 1893. The collection consists of well over 100 letters discussing the mental illness of this young woman and showing the development and range of her illness over a period of fourteen years. The letters were written by her brother Alexander Ward (who was primarily responsible for her care), her aunt, Dr. John W. Fry (who housed and cared for her), and her nurse Harriet Farnell. Some are written by Fanny herself. In addition to the letters, the collection includes medical reports, commitment papers, and official letters from the Lord Chancellor’s Visitors Office. The letters and documents show that many had hopes for Fanny’s recovery. There are graphic descriptions of Fanny’s relapses, which necessitated confinement and restraint. Letters tell of Fanny writing lucid but extravagant letters to Queen Victoria or to philanthropists asking for donations to found a hospital in Madras, India. There is a reference to a Dr. Maudesley [sic] as having seen Fanny at the onset of her illness, probably referring to Dr. Henry Maudsley (1835-1918), the son-in-law of John Conolly and the well-known founder of the Maudsley Hospital in London. The letters provide a very personal chronicle of the pathology of a mentally ill person. The collection also includes bills and receipts for medical services rendered and financial records pertaining to the Ward family’s account. A small amount of material relates to Fanny’s brother, Charles James Ward, who also suffered from mental illness and died in 1883. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
- No series
  - Bills for Fanny Ward’s expenses for 1877-1878 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Fanny Ward’s sister, Madeline and letters from her brother, Alexander, re: Fanny Ward’s care, board, illness and billing, and letters from C. N. Hodge, 1879 - 1883 (Box 1)
  - Letters written by Harriet Farnell, Fanny’s nurse, to Madeline and Alexander Ward re: Fanny Ward’s violent attacks, diet, etc. and Miss Farnell’s care, 1881 - 1882 (Box 1)
  - Letters of financial accounts and letter written by Harriet Farnell, 1882 (Box 1)
  - Monthly financial accounts for Fanny Ward’s nursing care, 1882 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Harriet Farnell to Fanny Ward’s sister, 1882 (Box 1)
  - Letters written by Fanny Ward mentioning insanity, 1882 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Fanny Ward, 1883 (Box 1)
  - Bills for Fanny Ward’s nursing services and clothing, 1881 - 1884 (Box 1)
  - Letters from John W. Fry (Fanny Ward’s doctor) to Alexander Ward re: Fanny Ward’s care and illness and receipts, 1884 (Box 1)
  - Letters from John W. Fry to Alexander Ward re: Fanny Ward’s care and illness and letter written by Fanny Ward and receipt, 1885 (Box 1)
  - Letters from John W. Fry to Alexander Ward re: Fanny Ward’s care and illness, 1886 (Box 1)
  - Letters from John W. Fry to Alexander Ward re: Fanny Ward’s care and illness and letters from Fanny Ward complaining of treatment, 1886 (Box 1)
  - Receipts for care of Fanny Ward, 1885 - 1886 (Box 1)
  - Bills and receipts for care of Fanny Ward, 1886 (Box 1)
  - Receipts to pay for the care of Fanny Ward, 1887 - 1888 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence between John W. Fry and Alexander Ward re: Fanny Ward’s care and illness and receipts, 1887 (Box 1)
  - Extract from order re: custody of Fanny Ward committed to her brother and sister, Alexander and Janet Ward, respectively, 1887 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence between Alexander Ward and John W. Fry and others re: Fanny Ward’s care and illness and receipt, 1888 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence between Alexander Ward and lawyers from the Lord Chancellor’s Visitors Office and court order re: Fanny Ward’s stock dividends, 1888 - 1893 (Box 1)
  - Letters from John W. Fry to Alexander Ward and letters with others re: Fanny Ward’s care and illness and receipts, 1889 (Box 1)
  - Thirteen telegrams re: Fanny Ward’s condition, 1886 - 1892 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence between John W. Fry and Alexander Ward re: Fanny Ward’s care and illness and correspondence with others, 1890 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence between John W. Fry and Alexander Ward re: Fanny Ward’s care and illness, 1891 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of Alexander Ward, James Adam and John W. Fry re: condition of Fanny Ward, 1891 - 1892 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence between John W. Fry and Alexander Ward and others re: Fanny Ward’s care and illness, 1892 (Box 2)
  - Letters written by Eveline S. Collier to Fanny Ward’s sister about Fanny Ward’s condition and letter written by Fanny Ward in reply, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence of Fanny Ward, Alexander Ward, and Eveline S. Collier, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Eveline S. Collier to Fanny Ward’s sister re: Fanny Ward’s condition and letter from Fanny Ward, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Statement and letter re: amount to be spent on maintenance of Fanny Ward, 1893 (Box 2)
  - Letters from Fanny Ward re: India Hospital plans, Undated (Box 2)
  - Letters from Fanny Ward, Undated (Box 2)
  - Letters from Janet Ward, Fanny Ward’s sister, Undated (Box 2)
  - Letters by Harriet Farnell re: condition of Fanny Ward, Undated (Box 2)
  - Undated letters from C. W. Hodge, Eveline S. Collier and Fanny Ward’s sister (Box 2)
  - Lord Chancellor’s Visitors Office and letters from lawyers to Alexander Ward re: estate, care of Fanny Ward, stocks, bonds and dividends, 1885 - 1893 (Box 2)
  - Letter re: investment of 250 pounds in Amsterdam Marine Insurance Co., 1895 (Box 2)
  - Letters re: illness of Fanny Ward’s brother, Charles James Ward and other papers relating to him and receipts, 1882 - 1883 (Box 2)